Guide to the Deena Stryker photographs, 1963-1964 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Deena Stryker photographs 1963-1964 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stryker, Deena.
6.5 linear feet Extent: 2579 Items
Journalist and photographer. The Deena Stryker photographs collection contains photographs, negatives, and contact sheets generated by the journalist then known as Deena Boyer during two trips to Cuba between July 1963 and July 1964, as well as exhibit prints produced in 2010. During her second trip to the island, Stryker interviewed and photographed Fidel and Raúl Castro as well as other major figures in the Cuban Revolution such as Che Guevara and Vilma Espín. Topics and photographic subjects include key members of the revolutionary government at work and relaxing; and life in Havana and in rural Cuba, focusing on shops, street scenes, rallies, farms, development projects, and schools. There is a draft of the book prepared for publication in Italian by Stryker about her Cuba trips. Stryker's original negatives were processed in Cuba by Alberto Korda, Fidel Castro's personal photographer. All of Stryker's negatives have been digitized and are available online. Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.01264
Language: Material in English and Spanish
Administrative Information
Online Items
Images from this collection are available in the Deena Stryker Photographs - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Deena Stryker photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2008.
Biographical Note
Deena Stryker (1933- ), formerly Deena Boyer, was born in the United States, received her Baccalaureate in Paris, and began work as a multilingual journalist at the Agence France-Presse in Rome in 1958. She lived in Poland and Hungry in the late 1960s where she worked in radio. She did graduate work in Global Survival and Future Studies at the University of Massachusetts from 1974 to 1975, and during the Carter administration was a speech writer for Joe Duffy, the Assistant Secretary of State for Cultural Affairs from 1977 to 1978. Stryker has lived and worked in France, Italy, Cuba, Holland, the United States, and Eastern Europe.
Collection Overview
The Deena Stryker Photographs collection spans the dates 1963-1964 and contains photographs and related material from Stryker's time in Cuba as a journalist for Paris Match. During her stay, she interviewed and photographed Fidel and Raúl Castro as well as other male and female leaders in the Cuban Revolution, including Ernesto Ché Guevara, Juan Almeida, Luis Crespo, Armando Acosta, Armando Hart Dávalos, Efigenio Ameijeiras Delgado, Faustino Pérez, Manuel Fajardo Sotomayor, César Escalante, Jesus Montane, Antonio Núñez Jímenez, Guillermo García Frías, Celia Sánchez, Ramiro Valdes Menendez, and René Vallejo.
The Photographic Materials Series contains Stryker's contact sheets, prints, and negatives created during the one-year period; all the photographic material processed by Alberto Korda, Fidel Castro's personal photographer. Topics and photographic subjects include key members of the revolutionary government, male and female, at work and relaxing with family members; life in Havana, including neighborhood and street scenes, and post-revolution housing projects; political rallies and meetings; and daily life and work in rural Cuba, particularly farms, agricultural workers, development projects, and schools. There are also images of Afro Cubans, religious life, and photos of major events such as the Havana trial of accused Batista collaborator Marcos Alfonso in March 1964, and the capture of Cuban fishing vessels by the U.S. Coast Guard in Feb. 1964.
The Correspondence Series contains letters of introduction to Fidel Castro from Stryker as well as one written by Sánchez and a diagram drawn by Raúl Castro. Stryker's analysis of the complexities of nascent post-revolution Cuba is captured in an Italian manuscript draft of the book she prepared for publication in Italy, housed in the Manuscript Materials Series.
An addition to the collection consists of prints produced from the original negatives by documentary photographer Cedric Chatterley for a 2010 exhibit on Deena Stryker's work, with a few other prints used in the exhibit created by Alberto Korda in the 1960s.
All of Stryker's negatives have been digitized and these images are available in their digital form. There are some prints and contact sheet images not represented digitally. Digital images and captions created by the photographer have been transferred to a library server.
Acquired by the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Original negatives are closed to research use. Please consult with a reference archivist for reproduction requests.
Subject Headings
Stryker, Deena; Castro, Fidel, 1926-; Castro Ruz, Raúl, 1930-; Espín, Guillois, Vilma, 1930-2007; Guevara, Ernesto, 1928-1967; Korda, Alberto, 1928-2001; Cuba -- Description and travel; Cuba -- Economic conditions -- 1959-1990; Cuba -- Foreign relations -- 1959-1990; Cuba -- History -- 1959-1990; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1959-1990; Cuba -- Social conditions -- 1959-1990; Havana (Cuba) -- Social conditions -- 1959-1990; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Contact sheets; Negatives; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1963 and undated, (1 folder; 3 items)
  Contains a letter from Stryker to Fidel Castro inquiring about the possibility of interviewing him, a letter of introduction for Stryker written by Celia Sánchez, and a sketch of the Cuban military command structure hand-drawn and signed by Raúl Castro.
  - 1963 July, 1963 Dec., and undated (Box 1)
- Manuscript Materials Series, undated, (3 folders)
  Contains an edited draft of Cronache dall'isola dei diavoli rossi, Stryker's unpublished Italian manuscript account and analysis of Cuban politics and society based on her time there; it became the basis for When the revolution was young, published in 2004.
  - Book manuscript, undated (in Italian), (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Photographic Materials Series, 1963-1964 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Consists of contact sheets, prints, and negatives of photographs taken by Stryker while in Cuba from December 1963 to June 1964. Captions were created by the photographer. All photographic films were processed by Alberto Korda, Cuba's official photographer during the revolution. Series includes numerous photographs of Fidel Castro acting in his official role, speaking at rallies and parades, visiting farms, and awaiting the return of Cuban fishing boats detained by the U.S. government. In addition, Stryker documents Fidel Castro relaxing at home with friends, exercising, and writing. Other prominent revolutionaries and government individuals photographed include: Ernesto Ché Guevara, Juan Almeida, Luis Crespo, Armando Acosta, Armando Hart Dávalos, Efigenio Ameijeiras Delgado, Faustino Pérez, Manuel Fajardo Sotomayor, César Escalante, Jesus Montane, Antonio Núñez Jímenez, Guillermo García Frías, Celia Sánchez, Ramiro Valdes Menendez, and René Vallejo.
  Other photographs chronicle life in Havana, including Carnaval, as well as the Cuban countryside, particularly the Sierra Madre and Isla de Turiguanó, Bayamo, Camagüey, and Guamá. Two rolls of film document the damage to cane fields and villages in rural Cuba in the aftermath of Hurricane Flora in late 1963. Many of the contact sheets are annotated. Negatives, contact sheets, and prints are organized sequentially by film roll; uncategorized prints and prints without negatives appear at the end of the series. All of Stryker's negatives have been digitized and these images are available in their digital form. There are a few prints and contact sheets not represented digitally.
  - Negatives Subseries, 1963-1964 and undated, (2 negative boxes) (Box 1)
    - Original negatives (closed to use) (Box 1)
  - Contact Sheets and Prints Subseries, 1963-1964 and undated, (1 box) (Box 2)
    - (Guamá) Indian village at Playa Girón (contact sheets 1-2), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Camagüey to Santiago, Holguín (contact sheet 3) (Box 2)
    - Birán, Santiago de Cuba, and Castillo del Morro (contact sheets 4-5), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Mayarí and Santiago de Cuba (contact sheet 5B) (Box 2)
    - Palma Soriano (contact sheet 6) (Box 2)
    - Palma Soriano and Bayamo (contact sheet 7) (Box 2)
    - Bayamo at night (contact sheet 8) (Box 2)
    - Rio Cauto (contact sheets 9-10), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Guamá (contact sheet 11) (Box 2)
    - Sierra (contact sheet 12) (Box 2)
    - Sierra and Turiguanó (contact sheets 13-14), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - January 1st national holiday (contact sheets 15-17), (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Manuel Fajardo Sotomayor and Edith Gombos (contact sheet 18) (Box 2)
    - School in ex-president Prio's house, Makarenkos, and Jimenez (contact sheet 19) (Box 2)
    - Jesus Montane, Luis Crespo, and Makarenkos (contact sheet 20) (Box 2)
    - Ana Betancourts, Havana, and classroom in Miramar (contact sheet 21) (Box 2)
    - Siomarra Sanchez, girls (contact sheet 22) (Box 2)
    - Faustino Pérez and Havana (contact sheet 23) (Box 2)
    - Ramiro Ramirito Valdés Menendez and René Vallejo (contact sheet 24) (Box 2)
    - Ernesto Ché Guevara, Juan Almeida, and Efigenio Almeijeiras Delgado (contact sheet 25) (Box 2)
    - Scuola d'Arte and René Vallejo (contact sheet 26) (Box 2)
    - Scuola d'Arte and Cubanacán (contact sheets 27-28), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Raúl Castro at home (contact sheet 29) (Box 2)
    - Fisherman with Fidel Castro (contact sheet 31-32), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Fidel Castro and Giangiacomo Feltrinelli on terrace (contact sheet 34) (Box 2)
    - Fidel Castro on terrace (contact sheet 34B) (Box 2)
    - Fidel Castro writing with Armando Acosta (contact sheet 35) (Box 2)
    - Luis Crespo, Celia Sánchez, and Havana (contact sheet 36B) (Box 2)
    - Carnival in Havana, Miss Estrella, and altar (contact sheet 36) (Box 2)
    - Carnival in Havana (contact sheet 37-38), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Guillermo García, Rita Longo (contact sheet 39) (Box 2)
    - Havana (contact sheet 40) (Box 2)
    - Marcos Rodriguez trial (contact sheet 41) (Box 2)
    - Marcos Rodriguez trial and Ernest Hemingway room (contact sheet 42) (Box 2)
    - Habana Libre and Havana at night (contact sheet 42B) (Box 2)
    - Santa Maria Spiaggia (contact sheet 43) (Box 2)
    - Motel Pinar, San Cristobal (contact sheet 44) (Box 2)
    - Pinar del Río landscapes, mogotes (contact sheet 45) (Box 2)
    - Tobacco, Pinar del Río, and coast (contact sheet 46) (Box 2)
    - Celia Sanchez and Carlos Rafael Rodriguez (contact sheet 47) (Box 2)
    - Habana del Este (contact sheet 48) (Box 2)
    - César Escalante and Faustino Peréz (contact sheet 49) (Box 2)
    - May 1st, Carlos Rafael Rodriguez, and presidential palace (contact sheet 50) (Box 2)
    - May 1st May Day (contact sheets 51-51B), (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - San Cristobal, Pinar del Río (contact sheet 52) (Box 2)
    - La Güira, San Cristobal, Habana Libre Pool (contact sheet 53) (Box 2)
    - Dance hall, Prado at night, Polynesio Restaurant (contact sheet 54) (Box 2)
    - Concert and Havana (contact sheet 55) (Box 2)
    - Habana Libre, night; Malecón; and Siomarra Sanchez (contact sheet 57) (Box 2)
    - Old Havana (contact sheet 58) (Box 2)
    - Malecón, Old Havana, and Armando Hart (contact sheet 58B) (Box 2)
    - Trinidad (contact sheet 59) (Box 2)
    - Santiago press conference (contact sheet 60) (Box 2)
    - Unsorted photographs (Box 2)
    - Photographs without negatives (Box 2)
- Exhibit Prints Series, (3 boxes)
  Most of these black-and-white gelatin silver prints were produced by documentary photographer Cedric Chatterley expressly for a 2010 exhibit on Stryker's work. The prints were derived from Stryker's original negatives housed in this collection; others were derived from prints produced earlier by Alberto Korda. The prints in the first set (boxes 3-4) are in window mats and were the final selection chosen for hanging in the 2010 exhibit. The rest of the prints (Box 5) are unmatted. In this box there is one set of 10 prints produced by Chatterley, with two duplicate sets; plus, The number of duplicates for an image is noted in parentheses following the original exhibit print.
  - Matted Exhibit Prints Suseries
    The 22 black-and-white prints in boxes 3 and 4 measure 7x10.5 in. and are mounted in 16x22 mats. One set of 22 duplicate unmatted prints are located in box 5.
    - Fidel Castro showing Comandante Armando Acosta his cows, Havana Province, February, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate exists) (Box 3, Image 1)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R3-E330
    - Fidel Castro among crowd waiting for return of fishermen held by U.S. Coast Guard, Havana, February, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 2)
      Orig. print number: 6666673-R3-E219
      Fidel Castro at the Paula Pier in Havana harbor awaiting the return of crew members from four Cuban fishing vessels captured by the United States Coast Guard
    - Treason trial of Marcos Rodriguez, Havana, March, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 3)
      Orig. print number: 6666663-R3-E350
      The trial of Marcos "Marquitos" Rodriguez Alfonso, who was accused of working for dictator Fulgencio Batista's secret police in 1957
    - Fidel Castro exercising on his apartment terrace in the Vedado section of Havana, February, 1964, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 3, Image 4)
      Orig. print number: 6666673-R3-E177
    - Raul Castro at home with daughter, February, 1964, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 3, Image 5)
      Orig. print number: 6666673-R3-E267
      Raul Castro and his daughter Deborah Castro Espín, the first of his four children with Vilma Espín Guillois, a fellow revolutionary and founder of the Cuban Women's Federation. This image provides a rare look at the father/daughter relationship. Raul Castro later became the President of the Cuban Council of State and the Council of Ministers. His daughter was an advisor to the Ministry of Education.
    - Celia Sanchez speaking to administrator of La Guira, Pinar del Rio Province, May, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 6)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R4-E457
      Celia Sanchez was the organizer of the first all female guerrilla brigade (Brigada Mariana Grajales) in the 26th of July Movement and a key official of the post-1959 government. She served as the Secretary to the Presidency of the Council of State, as a member of the National Assembly, a member of the Central Committee of the Cuban Communist Party, and was one of Fidel Castro's closest advisors. She directed many post-revolutionary construction projects and is shown here at the site of La Guira National Park.
    - Comandante Ernesto Che Guevara, in his office, Havana, February, 1964, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 3, Image 7)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R2-E291
    - Carlos Rodriguez, Havana, April, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 8)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R3-E395
      Carlos Rafael Rodriguez was a writer, economist and political protagonist whose activism crossed multiple phases of Cuban history. He participated in the overthrow of dictator Gerardo Machado in the 1930s; served as a Cabinet Minister under Fulgencio Batista in the 1940s and in 1958 negotiated an agreement between the Cuban Communist Party, of which he was a prominent member, and Fidel Castro in support of the overthrow of Batista. After 1959 he held various senior positions in the revolutionary government. Author Tad Szulc called him, "A most affable man of considerable learning and sophistication as well as a prolific writer, he has been Fidel's most valuable collaborator, politically and intellectually, since the 1959 victory."
    - Comandante Juan Almeida, Havana, February, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 9)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R2-E297
      Commandante Juan Almeida Bosque, one of the Cuban Revolution's most prominent commanders and perhaps the highest-ranking Afro-Cuban in a position of political leadership. Almeida was active in the Communist Party and served as Vice-President of the Cuban Council of State.
    - Comandante Ramiro Valdes, Ministry of the Interior, Havana, January, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 3, Image 10)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E596
      Commandante Ramiro Valdes, one of the original members of the revolutionary 26th of July Movement and Cuba's Vice President under Raul Castro.
    - Castro family graves, Biran, Holguin province, December, 1963, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 3, Image 11)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E188
    - Housing in Habana Este, Havana, January, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 12)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R1-E079
      After 1959, Havana expanded toward the east with construction of housing projects like La Habana del Este.
    - Café, store, Biran, Holguin Province, December, 1963, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 4, Image 13)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E206
      A café and store in Biran, Fidel Castro's home town. Biran lay within the zone of the U.S.-owned United Fruit Company.
    - Woman watching military parade, Havana, January, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 14)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E429
      Despite their relative lack of visibility in the revolutionary leadership after 1959, women played an important role in the struggle against Batista.
    - May Day Parade, Havana, May, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 15)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E382
      An image of Fidel rises behind a May Day parade. The quote says, "We have made a revolution greater than ourselves. Marxism-Leninism Lives!"
    - Concert entrance, Havana, April, 1964, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 4, Image 16)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R4-E446
    - Boy, Palma Soriano, Santiago de Cuba Province, December, 1963, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 4, Image 17)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E273
      Those who were born in the years before the Revolution and came of age within it, like this young boy photographed in Palma Soriano, occupy a unique sociological niche in Cuba's generational landscape.
    - Resort built on drained swamp near Bay of Pigs, Matanzas Province, December, 1963, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 18)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R1-E095
      Treasure Lagoon, a resort built on drained swamp near Bay of Pigs. The construction of new recreation facilities for workers reflected the Cuban government's interest in converting its lucrative and foreign dominated pre-revolutionary tourist industry for domestic use.
    - Western landscapes from car, December, 1963, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 19)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E227
      A view of construction in the eastern section of the country. The new government built throughout the island in an effort to reduce migration to the capital as occurred in other Latin American countries.
    - Makarenko students, Miramar section of Havana, January, 1964, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 4, Image 20)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E528
      A class at the Makarenko Teacher's Institute, founded as a training site for "revolutionary instructors." Many students were former participants in the 1961 Literacy Campaign. The campaign, which mobilized a quarter of a million young people to teach more than 700,000 rural Cubans to read and write, reduced the country's illiteracy rate from 23% to 4%
    - Boys looking at toys in shop window, Bayamo, Granma Province, December, 1963, (2 unmatted duplicates) (Box 4, Image 21)
      Orig. print number: 1092531-R3-E330
      Socialization to the values and icons of the new revolutionary society took place not only in schools but through popular culture products like toys and cartoons.
    - Clothing store, Havana, [window displays with shoppers, from street]May, 1964, (1 unmatted duplicate) (Box 4, Image 22)
      Orig. print number: 1092513-R4-E435
  - Unmatted Prints Subseries
    Box contains prints produced by Cedric Chatterley, documentary photographer, in 2010. There is one complete set of 22 duplicate prints of the matted prints in boxes 3-4; one set of 10 prints with different images that were used in the online exhibit (with 2 duplicate sets, for a total of 3 sets of 10 prints each); and one set of 9 prints that are selected second duplicates of the matted prints. The online exhibit also displays several images that are not present in the Exhibit Prints Series.
    - Duplicates of Matted Prints, (2 folders)
      - One set of 22 duplicate copies of the matted prints (see listing for boxes 3-4 for full titles and ids) (Box 5)
    - Other Prints, (3 folders)
      Three sets of 10 identical duplicates each.
      - Foyer, Habana Libre Hotel, Havana, 1964 (Box 5, Image 23)
        Orig. print number: 6666663-R3-E371
      - Altar for African rite, 1964 (Box 5, Image 24)
        Orig. print number: 1092513-R2-E279
      - Santiago, 1964 (Box 5, Image 25)
        Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E199
      - Tobacco workers, 1964 (Box 5, Image 26)
        Orig. print number: 6666663-R3-E255
      - Students living in former president Prio's house, 1964 (Box 5, Image 27)
        Orig. print number: 1092513-R2-E255
      - Guanabacoa, 1964 (Box 5, Image 28)
        Orig. print number: 6666673-R3-E261
      - Castillo del Morro, Santiago, 1964 (Box 5, Image 29)
        Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E162
      - Castro family home, Biran, 1964 (Box 5, Image 30)
        Orig. print number: 1092531-R2-E204
      - Raul Castro at home, Havana, 1964 (Box 5, Image 31)
        Orig. print number: 1092513-R2-E247
      - Vilma Espín, 1964 (Box 5, Image 32)
        Orig. print number: 1092513-R4-E494
        [Cuban revolutionary, chemical engineer, feminist, president of the Cuban Federation of Women from 1960 until her death. Married to Raul Castro in 1959, died in Havana in 2007.]
- Oversize Materials, (1 folder) (Box 5)
  Includes images of Fidel Castro from Paris Match, and an article on Cuba by Stryker from the Italian magazine Settimo Giorno (1963-1964).